All yours.
Okay. Thank you.
Hi everyone. My name is
and I'm presenting today with Adeline BC.
We are both graduate students
in the Digital Humanities program
at the University of Alberta.
Today we're going to be talking
about multi-player interactive
fiction experiences, the state of the
the challenges of cooperatively
authoring and designing
co-op play, our approach to it
and our project ether five.
Before going in, I'd like to acknowledge
that our project is partially funded
by the 2026 if micro Grant and supported
by the Crypt Research Lab
under the supervision of doctor P.B.
Berger.
The interactive fiction space is largely
populated with single player experiences.
So last year, as we were considering
submitting a game to check on 25,
we asked ourselves
what a cooperative interactive fiction
game would look like
and challenged ourselves to make one.
Looking into existing games and research,
we found that there's a small body of work
aiming in the direction,
but co-op and its authorship
remain critically unexplored.
Some of the earliest examples
are multi-user dungeons,
where a large number of players
can asynchronously inhabit a shared space
and interact with the world and each other
through text inputs or recent entries.
Modify tools like twine,
allowing one player to host,
and we want to host a shared session
that player to Canada join remotely.
Other approaches
include repeated code sharing
between players or, in the case
of Last Night with Alexis, grad players
are asked to choose different rules
and take choices at the same time.
In titles like the YOG,
you are one of four players in local co-op
taking turns to respond
as the game cycles through each character.
As we look at popular authorship
tools like twine, Inc.
in Form seven and read by,
we find that they're fundamentally
designed for a single player experiences
and do not support collaborative
authorship without complex workarounds.
On top of that, implementing
gameplay mechanics in these environments
is dependent on two specific
scripting languages and grammar,
which can often avionics newcomers
and is experienced as less intuitive
than more visual and interactive
approaches to dynamic logic building.
One of the more notable
research in the area is by Kalem Sport
from University of Southampton,
who builds on Mark Bernstein's version
of sculptural hypertext,
calling attention to its incompatibility
for authoring multiplayer, interactive
narrative experience or minds,
and outlines a new model called storyline.
Through this model, he breaks down
recurring interaction patterns and factors
we can use to evaluate and analyze them,
providing examples
of different relationships among nodes
in multiplayer branching narratives,
barriers and
Martineau takes inspiration
from small forts work and designs
a prototype recording the affordances
of such a system in action.
They mentioned that players
were highly interested in the experience,
but had difficulty
keeping track of the multiple dimensions
of information available,
so they focus on the public private
dichotomy of information
available to the two players,
and use an interesting hybrid setup
to solve this problem through players.
Side by side
to play the game on a single screen,
but also have their respective phones out,
which they used to interact with the game
and see information private to them.
Now, after looking at existing games,
research and tools, we've
identified three gaps.
Firstly,
there is currently no offering tool
that is designed to robustly support
collaborative authorship of co-op.
If existing literature lacks
in-depth discussions about tool
and interface design, and what
meaningful abstractions and features
are essential for such a potential
authoring environment.
As a result, the requirements
and complexities of designing
accessible software in this domain
still remain a largely unexplored topic
and a major barrier to authoring bias.
Secondly, while there are co-op,
if experiences null, combine
split screen local co-op
on a single machine with real time
multiplayer interaction and complex
shared states and gameplay mechanics
for meaningful interplay.
Agency.
Thirdly, existing knowledge on co-op
if design still remains
fragmented
and difficult to operationalize.
No consolidated coherent
framework, guideline or toolkit exists
that translates these findings
into practical design
principles for authors and developers,
so new creators are less to independently
reconstruct the design space and reinvent
solutions to recurring issues
such as managing synchronization,
information asymmetry, and interplay.
Agency with shared states.
Using our game ether five is a case study.
We argue that cooperative interactive
fiction
remains critically underexplored
and offer a design framework,
a writer first toolkit,
and an auto ethnographic analysis
to advance its creative, technical
and theoretical potential.
So our game ether five is a cyberpunk
split screen co-op interactive fiction,
where two players take on the roles
of ninth and Beck's queer cyborgs
surviving in the city of curio as they
navigate and plan against the Queer
Relocation Federation's initiative for off
planet rehabilitation of strange bodies.
Many games inspired us in our journey
to create ether five,
but there are a few worth mentioning for
their critical relevance to the project.
Disco Elysium, Citizen
Sleeper and Baldur's Gate
three were key inspirations for OPEC.
They are text heavy narrative adventures
that use TRP mechanics
that inspired our game greatly.
Depression
quest is locked and it's locked out.
Dialog options
where we wanted to implement in our game
is a way to have each player's choices
impact the other.
Realistic Kissing
Simulator inspired us to challenge
conventional mechanics
in games and explore queer game design,
forcing players
to interact in close proximity.
Additionally, Ivan PGS,
which are rich with branching
narratives
and heavily weighted in game decisions.
We also took a course on interactive
storytelling with doctor PB,
who gave us the opportunity to explore
game development with different mediums.
And Becs
are intrinsically queer characters
bound by a co-processor,
although their relationship beyond
that is subject to interpretation.
Likewise, the players are bound
to the same screen, sharing inventories
and locked out of decision options
based on what the other player is doing.
This forced proximity is reminiscent
of games like Realistic Kissing Simulator,
which forces players into an intimate play
style.
Boberg states that queer game design
is the practice of deliberately using game
mechanics and other design elements
to challenge normative expectations around
gender, sexuality, and the established
logics of digital gameplay.
Players of ether
five are not individuals with
independent parallel stories,
but instead interweave their experiences
through shared choices,
items, and proximity.
It was important to us
that as our game developed,
we moved beyond parallel narratives
and into something more intricate
and intimate so that the characters bond
is demonstrated not just in the narrative,
but in the mechanics as well.
The processor makes you work together
to share resources and lean on each other
in intimate ways.
It's not just about shared space,
but about shared materiality
and shared constraints.
Our goal is to create
an embodied experience of what it means
to lose out on choices that matter to you.
As stated by Piercey and Virga,
utilizing experiential play allows us
to examine what Brandon Quixote calls
the coming together of hardware,
flesh, and audio visuals.
In this project,
we experiment with auto ethnographic
exploration through co-op play
and collaborative authorship.
We examine how meaning emerges
through negotiated decisions, shared
spatial perception,
and asymmetrical narrative knowledge
between players and electronic literature.
Nodding to Sarah Ahmed, we reflect on
how bodies as well as objects, take shape
through being oriented toward each other
as an orientation that may be experienced
as the cohabitation of sharing space
or sharing of space.
As such, the queer narratives in ether
five push what it means
to be queer with more
than just the POV of one character.
We ask, what does it mean
to experience a queer narrative together?
Now, as
we're exploring the answers
to some of these recurring questions,
one of the more immediate questions
we were asking was,
can we build a toolkit,
an ecosystem of tools where the barriers
to implementing copious
where are modularized and supported.
And Godot became our engine of choice
for several reasons.
It has a strong willed, documented
UI library, which makes it well suited
for building text to the interfaces
and for communicating TPG mechanics,
and it manages to remain lightweight
and accessible without compromising
some of the capabilities
of modern game engines, which we thought
was essential for scalability,
innovation and experimentation
in the design space moving forward.
So how do we write this game together
efficiently?
Our initial approach was a custom
dialog manager designed to power
stacks from a JSON file
with right side by side in a CSV
tagging passages and choices
from a predefined set of options.
And our pipeline
would convert the CSV to JSON
and have our dialog manager parse
and render the text and choices
and their relationships in each player's
respective panels.
But while this works
for very simple mechanics,
anything more complex would require
a more sophisticated scripting grammar
or a new authoring environment
designed from the ground
up to create a more intuitive,
collaborative experience.
Another interesting
challenge we faced,
and perhaps the more fun one to solve,
is that Godo does not support simultaneous
multi-user control of UI components.
To solve this issue,
and to make it easy for new developers
to make local co-op experiences in go.
We developed to go to plugin
called Dual Cursor UI,
which we're actively working on
and refining.
Dual cursor
UI gives each player their virtual cursor.
We had a custom routing layer,
which bypasses go to native
button controls and takes over managing
all interaction events and UI states.
This also allows us to create
UI panels that have distinct ownership
properties, such as a dice pool
that only one player can access at a time,
so it should deny player entry
if the other player is already using it.
Panels containing dialog choices
which are specific to each player,
or shared panels containing special co-op
abilities, which both players
need to access and trigger
at the same time.
To activate, or panels
which contain choices
that lets both players enter
but only registers the first choice made.
Now, as we continue to work on ether five
and this project,
we have a few milestones planned.
Firstly, we recently got our project
project accepted to ACM hypertext
and we're looking forward to
showcasing our demo there this September.
We also want to finish developing ether
five and publish it on steam,
and each as a mechanics
heavy example of split screen local co-op.
We also want to publish an author
first resource
that translated consolidates
our findings into and learnings
into practical design
principles and guidelines for new co-op
makers and presents it in a coherent,
accessible format.
We are also exploring feasible designs
and architectures for a potential
collaborative authoring tool for co-op,
which we lovingly refer to as intertwined.
We think this space holds
immense potential for a new subgenre
of interactive fiction experiences
and electronic literature, and we aim
to continue developing this research.
Thank you.